Guide to the Esse Quam Videri Records, 1958-1968
Esse Quam Videri Records,1958-1968
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Esse Quam Videri.
2005-92
1
2 archival boxes and one oversize folder.
The fraternity Esse Quam Videri (EQV) was formed at Wesleyan in 1959 from the Phi Gamma chapter of Alpha Chi Rho (AXP). It was created in response to perceived discriminatory practices by the national AXP organization. EQV existed until 1967, when a house fire appeared to be a major factor in the demise of the group.
The collection contains a history of the origins, middle years, and end of EQV, biographies of some members, and a directory of AXP and EQV members, classes of 1957-1970. It also contains account books, newsletters, lists of members, correspondence, and three group photographs.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Donation by Jan Van Meter, 2005, and Patrick Lawler, 2005.
Historical Note
The EQV freshman rushing booklet of 1961 states:... In rushing we are not hindered by any discriminatory provision; rather our criterion for selection is based upon obtaining in EQV a diversity of personalities, talents, and interests.
The Wesleyan fraternity EQV was formed in September 1959 when Wesleyan's Phi Gamma chapter of Alpha Chi Rho (AXP) voted to withdraw from their national organization. This move was the result of discrepancies between AXP's exoteric, or external manual, and its esoteric manual, describing the oaths to be taken by pledges during their initiation. AXP had been founded in 1895 as a Christian fraternity. In 1954 the national organization changed the language of the exoteric manual from... membership from among Christians only to a requirement that members respect Jesus of Nazareth as their moral exemplar. The esoteric manual, however, kept the original language. For that reason, members of Wesleyan's Phi Gamma chapter chose to withdraw from the national organization. EQV stands for Esse Quam Videri, which is Latin for to be, rather than to seem.
EQV was supported by many Phi Gamma alumni who voted to change the by-laws to allow Wesleyan to lease, and eventually own the AXP building at 300 High St. EQV remained there until the fall of 1965. By this time, AXP had successfully petitioned the administration to return to campus and reclaim their house. EQV now needed a new home. For the 1965-1966 year, they lived in the dormitories on Lawn Avenue, and in September 1966 they moved into the John Wesley House at 343 High Street. The group may have lost momentum following a house fire in early December 1967. EQV disbanded in the spring of 1968.
Collection Overview
This collection contains two series representing donations by two EQV members. The first series is composed of original materials such as account books, tax forms, correspondence and newsletters. Much of this series is from 1967. This series also contains group photographs of members for the years 1960, 1966, and 1967. Series II is composed of secondary sources including a history of the fraternity, biographies of some members, and a directory. Appendices to the history have photocopies of original documents that are represented in Series I.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Alpha Chi Rho.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.); Greek letter societies--History.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students--History.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Esse Quam Videri.; Alpha Chi Rho. Phi Gamma Chapter (Wesleyan University) .
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I
  - House Bills, 1959-1968 and undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, taxes, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Account book, [1960]-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Account book, 1967 spring (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Account book, 1967 spring (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Account book, [1967 spring?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Group photographs, 1960, 1966-1967 (Box oversize, Folder 1)
- Series II
  - EQV: a history, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - History of EQV: appendix B, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - History of EQV: appendix C, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Biographies, [2005] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Directory from classes of 1957-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)